

Manoj Kumar

Email: manoj.shemar@gmail.com

Digital Portfolio links: https://manojshemar.github.io/

Phone No.: 6283844778

Key Skills



ABOUT

An enthusiastic Designer/Developer/IT Trainer who strives to create applications as well as the professional life of my students. I am always ready to learn technologies to enhance my knowledge. Tech-savvy, versatile and self-directed Technology Teacher with 18 years of experience in the field of education. Highly adept in providing professional development integrating technology into existing curriculum and creating new lesson plans to encompass technology in all classrooms. Excellent organizational and team building skills distinguished by commended performance and proven results.

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

- Working as Head of Department in Information Technology since February 2003 at Lally Infosys.
- Worked as Faculty in About Us Incorporates from August 2000 till 02 February 2003.

Soft Skills



TECHNICAL SKILLS

- NET TECHNOLOGIES (C#.NET, VB.NET, XML.NET)
- JAVA (J2SE-J2EE (STRUTS-SPRING FRAMEWORKS)
- WEB TECHNOLGIES USING ASP.NET MVC, JSP, SERVLETS, JSF, PYTHON Django, ReactNative, Flutter
- Data Management and Tools (SQL Server 2014, MySql, SQLLite, Hibernate using HQL Commands, Persistence using PQL Commands, LINQ)
- MOBILE APPLICATIONS DEVELOPMENT USING ANDROID
- DATA ANALYSIS
- HARDWARE EVALUATION

PROJECTS UNDERTAKEN

- Web Application for Blood Bank using spring in J2EE.
- Website of lally Infosys http://www.lallyinfosys.com
- Website of the jatt Sikh council (NGO) http://www. http://thejatsikhcouncil.com
- Website of Taste of Punjab Canada http://www.http://tasteofpunjabltd.ca
- Website of Fikre-Hondh (NGO) http://www.http://fikrehondh.com
- Mobile Application for Beggar Finger Data Scan (Android) for Beggar Free Smart City

EDUCATION

- Master of Computer Applications (Lateral Entry), Computer Applications, 2008
 - Maharishi Dayanand University-Rohtak, HR
- Master of Science, Computer Science, 2006
 - Maharishi Dayanand University-Rohtak, HR
- Master of Arts-Economics, 1999
 - Doaba College (GNDU)-Jalandhar
- Bachelor of Arts-Economics, Political Science, 1997
 - Doaba College (GNDU)-Jalandhar
- Diploma in System Administration-Jalandhar
 - AboutUs Incorporates-Jalandhar

CERTIFICATES

- Got First Runner Up in Once Act Play In National Youth Festival Held at Chennai in 1998
- Got Second Position Certificate from GNDU in One Act Play in 1997.
- Certified Regular Blood Donor by Pehal NGO and SBTC Punjab from 2008.
- Got First Position Certificate by Rotary Club Of Jullundhur for Mono Acting in 1997
- Got Certificate for Typing from GEE DEE Commercial College Jalandhar In 1994.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

HEAD OF IT-DEPARTMENT, 02/2003 - TILL DATE

Lally Infosys - Jalandhar, Punjab

- Providing technical solutions to the trainees in various technologies like C, C++, Java (J2SE-J2EE), C#. NET, ASP. NET MVC, Python, Web Application Development, Mobile Application using Android.
- Created new lessons plans based on course objectives.
- System and Network Management.
- Conduct teacher trainings and seminars on new technologies.
- Team management
- Handling company websites, web pages and advertising on social media.
- Handing IT Projects development.
- Designing Marketing Material using Corel-Draw, Adobe Photoshop, and Adobe Illustrator.

FACULTY MEMBER, 08/2002 TO 02/2003

AboutUs Incorporates - Jalandhar, Punjab

- Taught Students C, C++, VB6.0, Oracle 9i, 10, Web Technologies like HTML, CSS, FrontPage, JavaScript, and ASP.
- Created new lessons plans based on course objectives.
- Project Management

PART TIME COMPUTER INSTRUCTOR, 05/2002 TO 02/2003

Mavav Sehyog Society - Jalandhar, Punjab

- Verified data integrity and accuracy
- Teaching Web Designing and Web Development
- Given Training to faculties on Oracle SQL-PLSQL Commands

COLLABORATION WITH OTHER ORGANISATIONS

- Doardarshan Kender Jalandhar Govt. Of India Invites me time to time for their Program on Technical Education)
- AIR (All India Radio) Govt. Of India Jalandhar invited me on Social Media Pros-Cons.
- Given Career Guidance Seminars in different Schools and Colleges.
- Given Seminar on .NET Technologies to Technical Faculties of PTUDEP Program Govt. Of Punjab.
- Taking Online Classes of Overseas Students.
- Participating in Social Activities for the betterment of the Society. (Tree Plantation, Signature Campaign like Anti-Terrorism Campaign, Anti Drug Campaign, Smart City Jalandhar Campaign, Female Foeticide Campaign, World Women Day Campaign, Punjabi Jan-Jagriti Rally to promote Punjabi Maa Boli, Traffic Rules Awareness Rally)
- Regular Blood Donor from last 10 years donating blood after every 6 Months, honored by Pehal an NGO on World Donor Day at DAV College for donating blood regularly.
- Taking Seminar on Responsive Website Development to Engg. Students from different Colleges and universities at Lally Infosys and also their campus (DAVIET-DAV Engineering College, DIPS College, Dr.B.R Ambedkar National Institute of Technology, GNDU Regional Campus of Engineering, GNDU

PROJECTS UNDERTAKEN

- Web Application for Blood Bank using spring in J2EE.
- Website of lally Infosys http://www.lallyinfosys.com
- Website of the jatt Sikh council (NGO) http://www. http://thejatsikhcouncil.com
- Website of Taste of Punjab Canada http://www.http://tasteofpunjabltd.ca
- Website of Fikre-Hondh (NGO) http://www.http://fikrehondh.com
- Mobile Application for Beggar Finger Data Scan (Android) for Beggar Free Smart City

EDUCATION

- Master of Computer Applications (Lateral Entry), Computer Applications, 2008
 - Maharishi Dayanand University-Rohtak, HR
- Master of Science, Computer Science, 2006
 - Maharishi Dayanand University-Rohtak, HR
- Master of Arts-Economics, 1999
 - Doaba College (GNDU)-Jalandhar
- Bachelor of Arts-Economics, Political Science, 1997
 - Doaba College (GNDU)-Jalandhar
- Diploma in System Administration-Jalandhar
 - AboutUs Incorporates-Jalandhar

CERTIFICATES

- Got First Runner Up in Once Act Play In National Youth Festival Held at Chennai in 1998
- Got Second Position Certificate from GNDU in One Act Play in 1997.
- Certified Regular Blood Donor by Pehal NGO and SBTC Punjab from 2008.
- Got First Position Certificate by Rotary Club Of Jalandhar for Mono Acting in 1997
- Got Certificate for Typing from GEE DEE Commercial College Jalandhar In 1994.

ACHIEVMENTS

Students trained under my guidance are placed in Government as well as private sectors. They are working as professionals in MNCs like Dell, Wipro, HCL, TCS, Cognate, Infosys, Accenture, KPMG etc. Below are the students mentioned who are working in MNCS:-

- Gaurav Bhardhwaj Technical Consultant , Deloitte USI (developergaurav@outlook.com)
- Ravneet Puri Systems Ananlyst, States of California (ravneetpuri7@gmail.com)
- Lovepreet Singh Software Developer, Deloitte (lovepreetsingh.3097@gmail.com)
- Simrandeep kaur Analyst in Canadian Food Inspection Agency, Government of Canada (simrandeepkaur090998@gmail.com)
- Vipanjeet Singh Application Ananlyst Northern Health, Britich Columbia, Canada (vipanjeet.singh@northernhealth.ca)
- Ripu Raman Senior Govt. Computer Teacher, Govt. Sr. Sec. Sofi Village, Jalandhar Cantt.
- Avneet Kaur Narula Senior Govt. Computer Teacher, Nehru Garden Govt. Sr. Sec. School, Jalandhar.

HOBBIES

- Work Out in Gym.
- Yoga, Walking
- Reading IT magazines.